Abdul Khalique Talpur | BE, MEng

https://github.com/AKTalpur +92-308-3558785 | abdulkhalique11@hotmail.com

PROFILE

I am an ambitious, persistent, and highly personable individual with a diverse educational and professional background. My professional experience, so far, has helped me to gain and polish my interpersonal skills by teaching, mentoring, doing research, acquiring sales, meeting task deadlines in a dynamic fast-paced environment, public dealing with consumers, and raising employee morale. Moreover, my technical background has made me a critical thinker, problem solver, and a change maker. With all these skills combined with a proactive personal attitude, I am looking forward to work for an organization where I will get opportunities to learn and grow, and where I will be considered an asset rather than a liability.

EDUCATION

MEng, Mechanical Engineering, Queen's University, Kingston, Ontario, Canada – 2018-19
BE, Mechatronics Engineering, SZABIST, Karachi, Sindh, Pakistan – 2012-17

CERTIFICATIONS

The Complete 2024 Web Development Bootcamp | Udemy / The App Brewery, London
Full Stack Web Development | eHunar / Ministry of IT and Telecom, Government of Pakistan

WORK EXPERIENCE

Lecturer - Karachi Institute of Economics and Technology, College of Engineering, Department of Mechatronics Engineering | Karachi, Pakistan - October 2022 to September 2023

- Designed, prepared, and developed courses, modules, and teaching materials as per the HEC and PEC standards followed by OBE compliance.
- Conducted classes, supervised SDPs, and took exams according to the institute's policies.
- Maintained course folders and organized educational trips to the industry for final-year students.

Sales & Application Engineer - MEC PVT LTD | Karachi, Pakistan - January 2022 to August 2022

- Performed sizing and selection of Baker Hughes Consolidated Brand Pressure Safety/Relief Valves, Thermal Relief Valves, and Masoneilan Control Valves, for both valve units and spares.
- Worked on a project for condition monitoring, data acquisition, and evaluation of over 100
 Control Valves at PRL Pakistan Refinery Limited, for preventive maintenance and replacement.
- Handled sales inquiries, maintained follow-ups & sales records, and made commercial quotations.

Manager – Wendy's, QSR Group Inc. | Ontario, Canada – July 2020 to September 2021

- Implemented strategies for quality control, process optimization and waste reduction.
- Supervised, coordinated, and delegated the execution of operational tasks.
- Ensured compliance with all company policies and procedures.

Crew Member (Team Lead) - Tim Hortons | Ontario, Canada - July 2020 to September 2021

- Trained, monitored, and reinforced food safety procedures to crew members.
- Supervised crew members and trained new employees.
- Maintained time, temperature, and operational logbooks.

Internship – Viscous.co and Bioniks | Karachi, Pakistan – April 2017 to May 2017

- Built product prototypes by 3D modeling and 3D printing.
- Participated in 3D object scanning and print material selection.
- Conducted material and product performance tests.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Software

VS Code, MS Office Suite, MATLAB/Simulink, AutoCAD, SolidWorks, LabVIEW, NI Multisim, Proteus

Programming Languages

HTML, CSS, JavaScript

C, C++, C#, Python, Java

PLC Ladder Logic, Lego Mindstorms NXT (Not eXactly C), BASCOM-8051 Assembly Language

INTERPERSONAL SKILLS

Persistence, Higher Education Teaching, Academic Research, Engineering Sales, Customer Service, Teamwork, Time Management, Team Management

INTERESTS AND HOBBIES

STEM, Renewable Energy Technologies, Environmental Remediation, Mathematical Modeling, Coding/Programming, Squash, Cricket, Movies, Piano, Photography, Touring, Hiking